let's talk about one of my favorite
topics yes the major advancements that
have happened in the field of using tiny
human brains you can grow in a literal
jar if you want to and have run a
computer which you can purchase if you
want to cortical ABS an Australian
company released the first computer that
you can purchase for about $30,000 which
is a pretty hefty price tag but I
imagine it will be purchased for
Laboratories primarily critical ABS is
not the first to do this final spark
another company May neurop platforms so
you can use brain organoids at a
distance and you can even watch them
think in real time on their website if
you want to critical ABS 2 is also going
to have remote use as an option from
their perspective they want it to be
energy conserving we know that AI
requires whole nuclear power plants to
power it these guys can do a lot of what
AI can do and they're also a lot less
power hungry the problems with using
them is that you do require complex
organ oids in order to do a lot of the
thinking we need it to do you need
diverse cell types but a complex brain
organoid is also going to be something
you need to communicate with what's been
used in computation has been flat
electrodes that the brain organoid is
essentially just sitting on that can
record electrical activity and can send
activity back remember they prefer
ordered signals and they can also get a
little dose of dopamine when they do
something right in this way they have
both punishment and reward to solve the
electrode problem problem this research
group used soft Metals something that
would not cause a great degree of damage
remember things that go in your brain
can also cause damage kind of like the
brain chips using these little electrode
spikes it actually worked better it
didn't damage the brain organoids the
same way that other electrodes would and
they were able to get better information
with a three-dimensional structure than
flat electrodes could as well this is
going to allow us to use larger more
complex brain organoids while still
maintaining that observation now on to
what it can do we know that these guys
could operate in 3D spaces quite well
they've had it control the body of a
virtual butterfly and they've had it
play Pong it is better than AI in that
area for this reason mapping of a 3D
world is something they can do but they
seem to have some of the same
limitations that we have too we cannot
pull up vast amounts of information
instantly
it's stored somewhere in our neurons and
we're a lot bigger than a brain organoid
for this reason using it for an llm a
social chat bot may not be the best use
of them but they can learn language I
imagine we could use it for agentic
learning or decision making and how to
process information when you're not
actively using a social llm but that is
asking a lot we're going to have to see
where this will go and what they're
going to be capable of with
vascularization and immunocompetence
being on the horizon I saw a prepub for
that I don't know how big they could get
I don't know how complicated they could
get but it is exciting when it comes to
the ethics you have to understand that
most of these advances come out of
medicine and most of the computation is
coming out of Private Industry
researchers do not feel the same way
about brain organoids it the public does
I do admire that it's spooky and it's
kind of fun but we do have to be
realistic are they
sentient quite possibly they've been
defined as such because they're capable
of having an experience in responding
they lack a brain stem they cannot meet
the medical definition of Consciousness
they have no sleep or wake cycle as for
the philosophical one I'm not sure how
we could demonstrate that they have a
concept of self as is they're they're
tiny and that's not enough brain matter
to become a functional human could that
be overcome one day if so what would
that look like could they ever achieve
Consciousness quite possibly there is
something that feels kind of wrong about
using human brains as a computational
tool and being sold but there's also a
lot of pretty awful things that humans
agreed with I'm not sure how to feel
about this but it's an evolving
landscape I guess we'll find out